Rockwell Kent
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Rockwell Kent papers
circa 1840-1993, bulk 1935-1961
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Kent, Rockwell
88.0 linear feet
The Rockwell Kent papers measure 88.0 linear feet and date from circa 1840 to 1993 with the bulk of the collection dating from 1935 to 1961. The collection provides comprehensive coverage of Kent's career as a painter, illustrator, designer, writer, lecturer, traveler, political activist, and dairy farmer.
Biographical Note
Rockwell Kent (1882-1971), an energetic and multitalented man, pursued many interests and careers during his very long and active life. At various times he was an architect, draftsman, carpenter, unskilled laborer, painter, illustrator, printmaker, commercial artist, designer, traveler/explorer, writer, professional lecturer, dairy farmer, and political activist.
While studying architecture at Columbia University, Kent enrolled in William Merritt Chase's summer school at Shinnecock Hills, Long Island. He then redirected his career ambitions toward painting and continued to study with Chase in New York. Kent spent a summer working and living with Abbott H. Thayer in Dublin, New Hampshire, and attended the New York School of Art, where Robert Henri and Kenneth Hayes Miller were his teachers.
Critically and financially, Kent was a successful artist. He was very well known for his illustration work--particularly limited editions of the classics, bookplates, and Christmas cards. He was a prolific printmaker, and his prints and paintings were acquired by many major museums and private collectors. During the post-World War II era, Kent's political sympathies resulted in the loss of commissions, and his adherence to artistic conservatism and outspoken opposition to modern art led to disfavor within art circles. After many years of declining reputation in this country and unsuccessful attempts to find a home for the Kent Collection, Kent gave his unsold paintings--the majority of his oeuvre--to the Soviet Union, where he continued to be immensely popular.
An avid traveler, Kent was especially fascinated by remote, Arctic lands and often stayed for extended periods of time to paint, write, and become acquainted with the local inhabitants. Between 1918 and 1935, he wrote and illustrated several popular books about his experiences in Alaska, Tierra del Fuego, and Greenland. In the 1930s and 1940s, Kent was much in demand as a lecturer, making several nationwide tours under the management of a professional lecture bureau; he spoke mainly about his travels, but among his standard lectures were some on "art for the people."
In 1927, Kent purchased Asgaard Farm at AuSable Forks, New York, in the Adirondacks, where he lived for the remainder of his life, operating a modern dairy farm on a modest scale for many years.
As a young man, Kent met Rufus Weeks, became committed to social justice, and joined the Socialist Party. Throughout his life, he supported left-wing causes and was a member or officer of many organizations promoting world peace and harmonious relations with the Soviet Union, civil rights, civil liberties, antifascism, and organized labor. Kent was frequently featured as a celebrity sponsor or speaker at fund-raising events for these causes. In 1948, he ran unsuccessfully as the American Labor Party's candidate for Congress. Kent's unpopular political views eventually led to the dissolution of his dairy business, resulted in a summons to appear before the House Un-American Activities Committee, and prompted the U.S. State Department to deny him a passport, an action that subsequently was overturned by the U.S. Supreme Court.
Kent wrote two autobiographies, This Is My Own (1940) and It's Me, O Lord (1955). In 1969, he was the subject of an oral history interview conducted by Paul Cummings for the Archives of American Art.
Date Event
1882 born, Tarrytown, New York
1887 death of Rockwell Kent, Sr.
1894-1896 attended Cheshire Academy
1895 toured Europe with Aunt Jo
1896 attended Horace Mann School, New York City
1900-1902 studied architecture at Columbia University
1900-1902 attended William Merritt Chase's summer school, Shinnecock Hills, Long Island
1903 studied with William Merritt Chase, New York City
1904 first sale of a painting
1904 met Rufus Weeks and attended first Socialist meeting
1905 lived and worked with Abbott H. Thayer, Dublin, New Hampshire
1905 first painting trip to Monhegan Island, Maine
1907 first one-man show, Claussen Galleries, New York City
1908 marriage to Kathleen Whiting
1908 studied with Robert Henri
1908 joined Socialist Party
1909 birth of Rockwell, III
1910 ran Monhegan Summer School of Art
1910 first trip to Newfoundland
1910 helped to organize first Independent Exhibition
1911 birth of Kathleen
1912 moved to Winona, Minnesota
1913 birth of Clara
1914 settled in Newfoundland
1915 deported from Newfoundland
1915 birth of Barbara
1917 served as full-time organizer and administrator of Independent Exhibition
1918-1919 in Alaska with son Rocky
1919 purchased Egypt Farm, Arlington, Vermont
1919 incorporated self
1920 publication of Wilderness
1920 birth of Gordon
1922 traveled to Tierra del Fuego
1924 publication of Voyaging
1925 trip to France
1925 divorced from Kathleen
1926 marriage to Frances Lee
1926 traveled to Ireland
1927 purchased Asgaard Farm, AuSable, New York
1927 editor of Creative Art
1927 helped organize National Gallery of Contemporary Art, Washington, D.C.
1929 sailed to Greenland on Direction
1930 publication of N by E
1932-1933 returned to Greenland
1934-1935 final trip to Greenland
1935 publication of Salamina
1936 trip to Puerto Rico
1937 trip to Brazil
1937-1938 Post Office Department mural commission and controversy over Eskimo-language message interpreted as encouraging Puerto Rican independence
1939 divorced from Frances
1939 General Electric Co. mural commission for New York World's Fair
1940 publication of This Is My Own
1940 marriage to Shirley Johnstone (Sally)
1942 solo exhibition, Know and Defend America, at Wildenstein Galleries, New York City
1946 elected to Executive Committee of American Labor Party
1948 congressional candidate, American Labor Party
1948 transferred ownership of dairy to remaining employees after boycott resulting from support of Wallace for president
1949 attended World Congress for Peace, Paris
1950-1958 denied U.S. passport; lawsuit, appeals, and Supreme Court decision reinstating right to travel
1953 testified before House Un-American Activities Committee
1955 publication of It's Me, O Lord
1958 one-man show at Hermitage Museum, Leningrad
1959 publication of Of Men and Mountains
1960 gift of Kent Collection to Friendship House, Moscow
1960 exhibition at Pushkin Museum, Moscow
1963 publication of Greenland Journal
1966 elected to Academy of Arts of the USSR
1967 awarded Lenin Peace Prize, Moscow
1969 oral history interview, Archives of American Art
1969 home at Asgaard destroyed by fire; papers survived with some water and smoke damage
1969 first installment of Rockwell Kent Papers donated to Archives of American Art
1971 died, Plattsburgh, New York
1971 gift of additional Rockwell Kent Papers to Archives of American Art
1979 gift of textile samples to the Archives of American Art
1996 gift of additional Rockwell Kent Papers to Archives of American Art
2000 death of Sally [Shirley Johnstone] Kent Gorton
2000 previously sealed correspondence of wives Frances and Sally (Series 1) opened to researchers
2001 gift of additional Rockwell Kent papers to the Archives of American Art from the Estate of Sally Kent [Shirley Johnstone] Gorton
Scope and Content Note
The Rockwell Kent papers measure 88 linear feet and date from circa 1840 to 1993 with the bulk of the collection dating from 1935 to 1961. The collection provides comprehensive coverage of Kent's career as a painter, illustrator, designer, writer, lecturer, traveler, political activist, and dairy farmer.
Circumstances surrounding the acquisition of the papers are highlighted in an article by Garnett McCoy ("The Rockwell Kent Papers," in the Archives of American Art Journal, 12, no. 1 [January 1972]: 1-9), recommended reading for researchers interested in the collection. The collection is remarkably complete, for in the mid 1920s Kent began keeping carbon copies of all outgoing letters, eventually employing a secretary (who became his third wife and continued her office duties for the remainder of Kent's life).
Series 1: Alphabetical Files contain Kent's personal and professional correspondence, along with business records of the dairy farm and associated enterprises; also included are printed matter on a wide variety of topics and promotional literature relating to organizations and causes of interest to him. Voluminous correspondence with his three wives, five children, and other relatives, as well as with literally hundreds of friends, both lifelong and of brief duration, illuminates Kent's private life and contributes to understanding of his complex character. Among the many correspondents of note are: his art teachers William Merritt Chase, Robert Henri, and Kenneth Hayes Miller; fellow artists Tom Cleland, Arthur B. Davies, James Fitzgerald, Hugo Gellert, Harry Gottleib, Marsden Hartley, Charles Keller, and Ruth Reeves; collectors Duncan Phillips and Dan Burne Jones; critics J. E. Chamberlain and Walter Pach; and dealers Charles Daniel, Felix Wildenstein, and Macbeth Galleries. Kent corresponded with such diverse people as Arctic explorers Peter Freuchen, Knud Rasmussen, and Vilhjalmar Steffanson; composer Carl Ruggles and songwriters Lee Hays and Pete Seeger; civil rights pioneers Paul Robeson and Dr. W. E. B. Du Bois; writers Bayard Boyesen, Scott and Helen Nearing, and Louis Untermeyer; and art historian and print curator Carl Zigrosser.
Kent's interest and involvement in the labor movement are reflected in correspondence with officials and members of a wide variety and large number of unions and related organizations, among them: the Farmers' Educational and Cooperative Union of America, Farmers' Union of the New York Milk Shed, International Workers Order, National Maritime Union, and United Office and Professional Workers of America. Of special interest is his participation, often in leadership roles, in various attempts to organize artists. Files on the American Artists' Congress, Artists League of America, The Artists Union, United American Artists, and United Scenic Artists contain particularly valuable material on the movement.
A supporter of New Deal efforts to aid artists, Kent was actively interested in the various programs and often was critical of their limitations; he advocated continuing federal aid to artists after the Depression abated. The Kent papers include correspondence with the Federal Arts Project, Federal Fine Arts Project, Federal Writers Project, and the War Department, as well as correspondence with the Citizens' Committee for Government Art Projects and President Franklin D. Roosevelt on the subject.
Kent's professional correspondence documents exhibitions, sales, consignments, and reproduction of prints and paintings. He kept meticulous records of his advertising commissions and illustration work. Detailed correspondence with publishers and printers indicates Kent's involvement in the technical aspects of production and provides a good overview of the publishing industry during the mid-twentieth century.
Business records of Asgaard Farm include records of the dairy and transfer of ownership to its employees, tax and employee information, and documents concerning several related business ventures such as distributor ships for grain, feed, and farm implements.
Series 2: Writings consists of notes, drafts, and completed manuscripts by Rockwell Kent, mainly articles, statements, speeches, poems, introductions, and reviews. The Kent Collection given to Friendship House, Moscow, in 1960, was augmented later by a set of his publications and the illustrated manuscripts of many of his monographs. Also included are a small number of manuscripts by other authors.
Series 3: Artwork consists mainly of drawings and sketches by Kent; also included are works on paper by other artists, many of whom are unidentified, and by children.
Series 4: Printed Matter consists of clippings, exhibition catalogs and announcements, brochures, broadsides, programs, and newsletters. These include items by and about Kent and his family, as well as articles written and/or illustrated by him, and reviews of his books. There is also material on a variety of subjects and causes of interest to him. Additional printed matter is included among the alphabetical files, mainly as attachments to correspondence.
Series 5: Miscellaneous includes biographical material, legal documents, and memorabilia. Artifacts received with papers include textile samples, a silk scarf, dinnerware, ice bucket, and rubber stamp, all featuring designs by Rockwell Kent. Also with this series are a variety of documents including a phrenological analysis of an ancestor, lists of supplies for expeditions, a hand-drawn map of an unidentified place, and technical notes regarding art materials and techniques.
Series 6: Photographs includes photographs of Kent, his family and friends, travel, and art number that over one thousand. Also included here are several albums of family and travel photographs.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into six series. Series 1 is arranged alphabetically. The arrangement of the remaining series is explained in each series description. Note that sealed materials that became available in 2000 were microfilmed separately on reels 5740-5741, but have integrated into this finding aid.
Series 1: Alphabetical Files, circa 1900-1971, undated (Reels 5153-5249, 5256, 5740-5741)
Series 2: Writings, 1906-1978, undated (Reels 5249-5252, 5741)
Series 3: Art Work, 1910-1972, undated (Reels 5252, 5741)
Series 4: Printed Matter, 1905-1993, undated (Reels 5252-5254)
Series 5: Miscellaneous, 1859-1969, undated (Reels 5254, 5741)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1840-1970, undated (Reels 5254-5255, 5741)
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Art and war; Art, Modern -- 20th century -- United States -- Political aspects; Authors -- New York; Commercial art; Dairy farms; Designers -- New York (State); Federal aid to the arts; Illustration of books; Illustrators -- New York (State); Labor unions; Mural painting and decoration; Painters -- New York (State); Politics and culture; World War, 1939-1945 -- Art and the war; World War, 1939-1945 -- Civilian relief
Types of Materials:
Business records; Drawings; Photographs; Poems; Sketches; Works of art
Names:
Boyesen, Bayard; Cleland, T. M. (Thomas Maitland), 1880-1964; Chase, William Merritt, 1846-1916; Chamberlain, J. E.; Daniel, Charles, 1878-1971; Davies, Arthur B. (Arthur Bowen), 1862-1928; DuBois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1882-1945; Fitzgerald, James, 1899-1971; Freuchen, Peter, 1886-1957; Gellert, Hugo, 1892-1985; Gottlieb, Harry, 1895-; Hartley, Marsden, 1877-1943; Hays, Lee, 1914-1981; Henri, Robert, 1865-1929; Jones, Dan Burne; Keller, Charles, 1914-2006; Miller, Kenneth Hayes, 1876-1952; Nearing, Helen; Nearing, Scott, 1883-1977; Pach, Walter, 1883-1958; Phillips, Duncan, 1886-1966; Rasmussen, Knud, 1879-1933; Reeves, Ruth, 1892-1966; Robeson, Paul, 1898-1976; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945; Ruggles, Carl, 1876-1971; Seeger, Pete, 1919-; Stefansson, Vilhjalmur, 1879-1962; Untermeyer, Louis, 1885-1977; Wildenstein, Felix; Zigrosser, Carl, 1891-; Artists' Union (New York, N.Y.); Federal Art Project; Macbeth Gallery; United Scenic Artists; United American Artists; Artists League of America; United Office and Professional Workers of America; National Maritime Union of America; International Workers Order; Farmers Union of the New York Milk Shed; National Farmers' Union (U.S.); Federal Writers' Project; Citizens' Committee for Government Arts Projects; American Artists' Congress
Provenance
In 1969, Rockwell Kent donated his papers to the Archives of American Art; textile samples were received in 1979, and his widow gave additional papers in 1971 and 1996. Letters to Rockwell Kent from wives Frances and Sally, sealed during Sally Kent Gorton's lifetime, became available for research after her death in 2000, and further material was donated to the Archives of American Art in 2001 by the Estate of Sally Kent [Shirley Johnstone] Gorton.
Restrictions on Access
The microfilm of this collection has been digitized and is available online via AAA's website. Use of material not microfilmed or digitized requires an appointment.
Alternative Forms Available
The microfilm of this collection was digitized in 2008 and is available via the Archives of American Art's website. Researchers should note that the legibility of some materials is poor due to the microfilm quality.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Alphabetical Files, circa 1900-1971, undated, Series 1:; (Reels 5153-5249, 5256, 5740-5741)
  This series contains Kent's personal and professional correspondence, along with business records of the dairy farm and associated enterprises; also included are printed matter on a wide variety of topics and promotional literature relating to organizations and causes of interest to him. Voluminous correspondence with his three wives, five children, and other relatives, as well as with literally hundreds of friends--both lifelong and of brief duration--illuminates Kent's private life and contributes to understanding of his complex character. Among the many correspondents of note are: his art teachers William Merritt Chase, Robert Henri, and Kenneth Hayes Miller; fellow artists Tom Cleland, Arthur B. Davies, James Fitzgerald, Hugo Gellert, Harry Gottleib, Marsden Hartley, Charles Keller, and Ruth Reeves; collectors Duncan Phillips and Dan Burne Jones; critics J. E. Chamberlain and Walter Pach; and dealers Charles Daniel, Felix Wildenstein, and Macbeth Galleries. Kent corresponded with such diverse people as Arctic explorers Peter Freuchen, Knud Rasmussen, and Vilhjalmar Steffanson; composer Carl Ruggles and songwriters Lee Hays and Pete Seeger; civil rights pioneers Paul Robeson and Dr. W. E. B. Du Bois; writers Bayard Boyesen, Scott and Helen Nearing, and Louis Untermeyer; and art historian and print curator Carl Zigrosser.
  Kent's interest and involvement in the labor movement are reflected in correspondence with officials and members of a wide variety and large number of unions and related organizations, among them: the Farmers' Educational and Cooperative Union of America, Farmers' Union of the New York Milk Shed, International Workers Order, National Maritime Union, and United Office and Professional Workers of America. Of special interest is his participation, often in leadership roles, in various attempts to organize artists. Files on the American Artists' Congress, Artists League of America, The Artists Union, United American Artists, and United Scenic Artists contain particularly valuable material on the movement.
  A supporter of New Deal efforts to aid artists, Kent was actively interested in the various programs and often was critical of their limitations; he advocated continuing federal aid to artists after the Depression abated. The Kent Papers include correspondence with the Federal Arts Project, Federal Fine Arts Project, Federal Writers' Project, and the War Department, as well as correspondence with the Citizens' Committee for Government Art Projects and President Franklin D. Roosevelt on the subject.
  Kent's professional correspondence documents exhibitions, sales, consignments, and reproduction of prints and paintings. He kept meticulous records of his advertising commissions and illustration work. Detailed correspondence with publishers and printers indicates Kent's involvement in the technical aspects of production and provides a good overview of the publishing industry during the mid-twentieth century.
  Business records of Asgaard Farm include records of the dairy and transfer of ownership to its employees, tax and employee information, and documents concerning several related business ventures such as distributorships for grain, feed, and farm implements.
  Letters to Rockwell Kent from wives Frances and Sally (Shirley Johnstone), sealed during Sally's lifetime, became available for research in 2000 and were microfilmed later on reels 5740-5741.
  File titles are, in most cases, those used by Rockwell and Sally Kent, with some minor changes for consistency. The Kents' filing system included a "Miscellaneous" designation for each letter of the alphabet, used for single items or small quantities not requiring separate folders. To facilitate access and for ease of microfilm use, contents of the miscellaneous folders have been interfiled in sequence.
  Material is arranged alphabetically, usually by the name of the individual or organization represented, though some file titles represent subjects or occasions (e.g., "Spanish Causes" and "Birthday").
  Records are arranged chronologically within each file; brief summaries are provided for many titles, usually where there is a significant amount of material. Cross-referencing is supplied where possible to indicate areas of overlap, inconsistencies in filing, or name changes; references are to other file titles within this series.
  The bulk of this series has been digitized. Material of very specialized or limited interest (e.g. banking records, dairy immunization records, employee tax records, dog licenses etc.) has not been digitized.
  - Abbe, George and Barbara, 1958-1970 (Reel 5153, Frame 3-77)
    (concerning book jacket design for his novel, and request for help in finding a teaching position)
  - Abbott and Cobb, 1947 (Reel 5153, Frame 78-80)
  - Abbott, William Morris, 1961 (Reel 5153, Frame 81-85)
  - Abercrombie & Fitch Co., 1946 (Reel 5153, Frame 86-88)
  - Abercrombie, Frederick S., 1943 (Reel 5153, Frame 89-93)
  - Aberdeen Book Company, 1944 (Reel 5153, Frame 94-96)
  - Abraham & Straus, 1952 (Reel 5153, Frame 97-99)
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade (see also: Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade), 1941-1943 (Reel 5153, Frame 100-112)
  - Abraham Lincoln High School, 1942 (Reel 5153, Frame 113-116)
  - Abraham Lincoln School, 1944 (Reel 5153, Frame 117-124)
  - Abrahamson, Ben (Argus Book Shop), 1954 (Reel 5153, Frame 125-129)
  - Abroad, 1959 (Reel 5153, Frame 130-136)
    (correspondence with travel agent arranging trip to Europe)
  - A. C. A. Gallery, 1940-1944 (Reel 5153, Frame 137-151)
    (includes first issue of A. C. A. Art Letter)
  - Academy of the Arts of the U.S.S.R., 1962-1970 (Reel 5153, Frame 152-219)
  - Acker, Rikki (Mrs. Edward S. Acker), undated (Reel 5153, Frame 220-223)
  - Adamic, Mr., 1948 (Reel 5153, Frame 224-226)
  - Adams, Mrs. J. M., 1962 (Reel 5153, Frame 227-231)
  - Adams, Josephine Truslow, 1941 (Reel 5153, Frame 232-252)
    (regarding her dismissal from the Art Department of Swarthmore College, presumably for supporting liberal causes)
  - Adams, Margaret, 1965-1966 (Reel 5153, Frame 253-263)
  - Adamson, J. M., undated (Reel 5153, Frame 264-266)
  - Addison, Wilfred J., 1945 (Reel 5153, Frame 267-270)
  - Addresses Book, A-Z, 2 Alphabets (see also: Notes, Addresses, Phone Calls, etc.), circa 1930s-1940s (Reel 5153, Frame 271-408)
  - Addresses, Miscellaneous (see also: Notes, Addresses, Phone Calls, etc.), circa 1930s-1940s (Reel 5153, Frame 409-490)
  - Adelson Galleries, Inc., 1967 (Reel 5153, Frame 491-494)
  - Adirondack Moose River Committee, 1946 (Reel 5153, Frame 495-500)
  - Adirondack Mountain Club, 1946 (Reel 5153, Frame 501-508)
  - The Adirondack Museum, 1969 (Reel 5153, Frame 509-511)
  - The Adirondack Record, 1945 (Reel 5153, Frame 512-514)